[Music]
This is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
SE radio is brought to you by the ITE
computer society by it e software
magazine online at
computer.org/software.
[Music]
Hi everyone, I'm Priyanka Ragwan for
software engineering radio and I'm in
conversation with Abhinav Kimotei on
retrieval augmented generation or rag.
Abhinav is the co-founder and VP at yarn
an AI powered platform for content
creation and he's also the author of the
book a simple guide to retrieval
augmented generation. He has more than
15 years of experience in building AI
and ML solutions. And if you see today
large language models are being used in
numerous ways in various industries for
automating tasks using natural language
as input. In this regard, RAG is
something that is talked about to
enhance performance of LLMs. So for this
episode, we'll be using the book from
Abinav to discuss RAG. Welcome to the
show Abhinav. Hey, thank you so much
Priyanka. It's great to be here. Is
there anything else in your bio that I
missed out that you would like listeners
to know about? Oh, no, no, this is
absolutely fine. Okay, great. So, let's
jump right in. The first thing when I
gave the introduction, I talked about
LLMs being used in a lot of industries,
but the first section of the podcast, we
could just go over some of these terms.
And so, I'll ask you to define a few of
those things for us. So, what is a large
language model? That's a great question.
That's a great place to start the
conversation also. Yeah. So large
language models very important in a way.
LLM is the technology that ushered in
this new era of artificial intelligence,
right? Everybody's talking about it. I'm
sure by now everybody is familiar with
chat GPT and the likes. So these
applications which everybody's using for
conversations, text generation etc. The
core technology that they are based on
is a large language model, an LLM as we
call it. Technically, LLMs are deep
learning models. They have been trained
on massive volumes of text and they are
based on a neural network architecture
called the transformers architecture and
they're so deep that they have billions
and in some cases trillions of
parameters and hence they're called
large models. What it does is that it
gives them unprecedented ability to
process text, understand text and
generate text. So that's sort of the
technical definition of an LLM. But in
layman terms, LLMs are sequence models
or we can say that they are algorithms
that look at a sequence of words and are
trying to predict what the next word
should be. And how they do it is based
on a probability distribution that they
have inferred from the data that they
have been trained on. So think about it.
You can predict the next word and then
the word after that and the word after
that. So that's how they are generating
coherent text which we also call natural
language and hence they are generating
natural language. That's great. Another
term that's always used is prompt
engineering. So we've always a lot of us
who go on chat JPT or other kind of
agents you just type in normally but
then you see that there's lot of
literature out there which says if
you're good at prompt engineering you
can get better results. So what is
prompt engineering? Yeah that's a good
question. So LLMs differ from
traditional algorithms in the sense that
when you're interacting with an LLM
you're interacting not in code or not in
numbers but in natural language text. So
this input that you're giving to the LLM
in form of natural language or natural
text is called a prompt. So think of
prompt as an instruction or a piece of
input that you're giving to this model.
In fact, if you go back to early 2023,
everybody was saying, hey, English is
the new programming language because
these AI models, you can just chat with
them in English. And it may seem a bit
bananal if you look at it from a high
level that hey how can English now
become a programming language. But it
turns out the way you are structuring
your instructions even in English
language has a significant effect of on
the kind of output that this LLM will
produce. I mean English may be the
language but the principles of logic
reasoning they stay the same. So how you
craft your instruction that becomes very
important and this ability or the
process of crafting the right
instruction even in English language is
what we call prompt engineering. Great.
And then obviously the other question I
have to ask you is also there's a lot of
talk about this term called context
window. Yeah. What is that? As I said
right LLMs are sequence models. They
look at a sequence of text and then they
will generate some text after that. Now
this sequence of text cannot be infinite
and the reason why it can't be infinite
is because of how the algorithm is
structured. So there is a limit to how
much text can the model look at in terms
of the instructions that you are giving
it and then how much text can it
generate after that. So this constraint
on the number of well it's technically
called tokens but we'll use words. So
number of words that the model can
process in one go is called the context
window of that model. And we started
with very less context windows but now
there are models that have context
window of two lakhs and three lakhs. So
you know can process two lakh words at a
time. So that's what the context window
term means. Okay. I think now would be a
good time to also talk about what is
hallucination and why does it happen in
LLMs? When I was reading your book, the
first chapter, you give a very nice
example. If there are listeners on the
show, we have a listenership from all
over the world. But I had a very nice
example on your book on what is
hallucination and why it happens. And I
was wondering if you could use that. It
is with respect to trivia on cricket,
which is a game we play in the
subcontinent. But maybe you could
explain what is hallucination using
that. Yeah. Yeah. Thank you for bringing
that up and appreciating that example.
Let me first give the context of what
hallucinations are. So hallucination
means that whatever output the LLM is
producing it is factually incorrect and
it has been observed that in a lot of
cases when you ask an LLM a question it
will very confidently give you a reply
and if the reply consists of a factual
information as a user you will believe
that factual information to be accurate
but it is not guaranteed and in some
cases it might just be fabricated
information and that is what we call
hallucinations which is this
characteristic of an LLM to sometimes
respond confidently with inaccurate
information and like the example of the
cricket world cup that you were
mentioning is so chat GPT 3.5 or GPT 3.5
model was trained up till sometime in
2022 so that's when the training of that
model happened which means that you know
all The information that was given to
this model while training was only up
till that point. So if I asked that
model a question about the cricket world
cup that happened in 2023,
it sometimes gave me incorrect response.
It said India won the World Cup when in
fact Australia had won it and it gave it
very confidently. It gave the score
saying India defeated England by so many
runs etc. which is absolutely not true
which is false information which is an
example of what hallucinations are and
why do hallucinations happen that is
also a very important aspect to
understand about LLMs at the outset I'd
like to mention that LLMs are not
trained to be factually accurate as I
said they are just looking at the
probability distribution very in very
simplistic terms they are looking at the
probability distribution of words and
then trying to predict what the next
word in the sequence is going to be. So
nowhere in this construct are we
programming the LLM to also do a factual
verification of the claims that it is
making. So inherently that's not how
they have been trained but the user
expectation is that they should be
factually accurate and that's the reason
why they're criticized for these
hallucinations. So if you ask an LLM a
question about something that is not
public information, some data that they
might not be trained on, some
confidential information about your
organization or you as an individual,
the LLM has not been trained on that
data. So there is no way that it can
know that particular snippet of
information. So it will not be able to
answer that. But what it does, it
generates a factually inaccurate answer.
Similarly, these models take a lot of
data and time to train. So, it's not
that they're real time, they're updating
in real time. So, there is a knowledge
cut off date also with the LMS. But
despite all that, despite these
characteristics of training an LLM, even
if they have the data, they might still
generate responses that are not even
true to the training data because of the
nature of training. They're not trained
to replicate information. They're just
trying to predict the next one. So these
are the reasons why hallucinations
happen and there has been a lot of
criticism of LLMs and initially they
were also dismissed saying oh this is
not something that we can apply in real
world. Wow that's interesting. I never
expected that even when the data is
available that it could also be
factually incorrect. Okay that's
interesting to note. So this would be a
perfect time to actually get into what
is rag. So can you explain that to us is
what is rag and why is there a need for
rag? Right? Let's start with the need
for rag. We've talked about
hallucinations. The responses may be
suboptimal is they might not have the
information or they might have incorrect
information. In both cases the LLMs are
not usable in a practical scenario. But
it turns out that if you are able to
provide some information in the prompt,
the LLMs adhere to that information very
well. So if I'm able to again taking the
cricket example, say hey who won the
cricket world cup and within that prompt
I also paste the Wikipedia page of 2023
cricket world cup. the LLM will be able
to process all that information and find
out from that information that I have
pasted in the prompt that Australia was
the winner and hence it will be able to
correctly give me the response. So that
maybe you know a very naive example like
pasting this information in the prompt
and getting the result but that is sort
of the fundamental concept of rag. The
fundamental idea behind rag is if the
LLM is provided with the information in
the prompt, it will be able to respond
with a much higher accuracy. So what are
the different steps that this is done
in? If I were to kind of visualize a
workflow, suppose you're asking a
question to the LLM. Now instead of
sending this question directly to the
LLM, if this question can search through
a database or a knowledge base where
information is stored and fetch the
relevant documents. These documents can
be word documents, JSON files, any text
documents, even the internet and fetch
the right information from this
knowledge base or database. Then along
with this user question send this
information to the LLM. The LLM will
then be able to generate a factually
correct response. So these three steps
of fetching and retrieving the correct
information augmenting this information
with the user's question and then
sending it to the NLM for generation is
what encompasses retrieval augmented
generation in three steps. I think we'll
probably deep dive into this in the next
section of the podcast. But before that,
what I wanted to ask you was would you
be able to give us some examples in
industries which are using rag. Almost
everywhere that you are using LLM, an
LLM where there is a requirement to be
factually accurate, rag is being
employed in some shape and form.
Something that you might be using in
your daily life. If you are using the
search functionality on chat GPT or if
you're uploading a document to chat GPT
and sort of conversing with that
document that's an example of a rag
system similarly today if you go and ask
for something on Google you search
something on Google on the top of your
page you will get a summary sort of a
textual summary of the result which is
sort of an experimental feature that
Google has launched that is a prime
example of rag. It is looking at all the
search results and then passing that
those search results to the LLM and
generating a summary out of that. So
that's an example of rag. Apart from
that a lot of chat bots today are based
on rag because if a customer is asking
for some support then you this system
can look at support documents and
respond with the right item. Similarly,
virtual assistants like Siri have
started using a lot of retrieval in
their workflow. It's being used for
content generation, question answering
system for enterprise knowledge
management. If you have a lot of
information on your SharePoint or in
some collaborative workspace, then a
rack system can be built on this
collaborative workspace so that users
don't have to search through and look
for the right information. they can just
ask a question and get those knowledge
snippets. So it's being used in
healthcare, in finance, in legal, almost
in all the industries. A very
interesting use case is Watson AI was
using this for commentary during the US
Open tennis tournament because you can
generate commentary. You have live
scores coming in. So that is one thing
that you can pass to the LLM. You have
information about the player, about the
match, what is happening in other
matches, all of that. So this
information you pass to the LLM and
it'll generate a coherent commentary
which then from text to speech models
can also be converted into speech. So
that's where rag systems are being used
today. Great. So then I think that's a
perfect segue for me to also ask you one
last question before we move to the rag
enabled design which I want to talk
about. The question I wanted to ask you
is like is there a way humans can get
involved to make the rag perform better?
That's a great question. I feel the
state of the technology as it stands
today there is a need of a lot of human
intervention to build a good rack
system. Firstly the rag system is as
good as your data. So the curation of
data sources like which data sources to
look at whether it's your file systems
whether open internet access is allowed
which websites should be allowed over
there if is the data in the right is
there garbage in the data has it been
processed correctly all of that is one
aspect in which human intervention
becomes very important today. The other
is in a degree of verification of the
output. So drag systems exist but you
can't expect them to be 100% foolproof.
So until you have achieved that level of
confidence that hey your responses are
fairly accurate there is a certain
degree of manual evaluation that is
required of your rag system and then at
every component of rag whether your
queries are getting aligned with the
system you need a certain degree of
evaluation there is this whole idea of
which is not specific to rag but
reinforcement learning based on human
feedback which goes by the acronym RLHF
that is another important aspect that
human intervention is required in rag
systems. Okay, great. So the humans can
be used in both to find out how the data
is going into the system as well as like
verifying the output and also the rag
enabled design as well. You need the
humans to actually create the thing. Oh
absolutely. It can't be done by AI yet.
You need human beings to build the
system of course. Okay. So now I'd like
to ask you about what are the key
components required to build a rag. You
talked about the retrieval part, the
augmentation part and the generation
part. Yeah. So maybe you could just
paint a picture for us on that. Right.
So like you said these three components
like you need a component to retrieve
the right information which is done by a
set of retrievers. Very uninoative term
but it is done by retrievers. Then once
the documents are retrieved or
information is retrieved then there is a
component of augmentation where you are
putting the information in the right
format and we talked about prompt
engineering. So there's a lot of aspect
of prompt engineering in this
augmentation step and then finally it's
the generation component which is the
LLM. So you're sending this information
to the LLM that becomes your generation
component and these three in combination
form the generation pipeline. So this is
how the user interacts with the system
real time. This is that workflow. But if
you think sort of one level deeper into
this, there is this entire knowledge
base that the retriever is going and
searching through. So creation of this
knowledge base also becomes an important
component. So this knowledge base is a
key component of your rack system. And
creation of this knowledge base is done
through another pipeline known as the
indexing pipeline which is sort of
connecting to the source data systems
and processing that information and
storing it in a specialized database
format called vector databases. This is
largely an offline process a nonrealtime
process. You curate this knowledge base.
So that's another component. These are
the core components of this rack system.
But what is also important is evaluation
right is your system performing well or
you put in all this effort created the
system and is it still hallucinating? So
you need to evaluate whether your
responses are correct. So evaluation
becomes that another component in your
system. Apart from that security,
privacy, these are aspects that become
even more important when it comes to
LLMs because as we are entering this age
of artificial intelligence and more and
more processes will start getting
automated and reliant on AI systems and
AI agents. Data privacy becomes a very
important aspect. Your guardrailing
against attacks, malicious attacks, this
becomes a very important context. And
then to manage everything interacting
with the user there needs to be an
orchestration layer which is sort of
playing the role of that conductor
amongst all these different components.
So these are the core components of a
rack system. But there are other systems
other layers that can be part of the
system sort of experimentation and data
training and other models. So those are
more like software architecture layers
that you can also build around this rag
system. One of the big things about the
rag system is of course the data. So
talk us a little bit about the data like
you have multiple sources. Does data
have to be in a specific format and how
are they ingested? Right? You need to
first define what your rack system is
going to talk about, what your use case
is. And based on the use case, the first
step is the curation of data sources,
right? Which source systems should it
connect to? Is it just a few PDF files?
Is it your entire object store or your
file sharing system? Is it the open
internet? Is it like a third party
database? So, first step is curation of
these data sources. what all should be a
part of your rack system and rack works
best or even like when we are using LLMs
the key use case of LLMs is unstructured
data for structured data you already
have everything solved almost right like
in traditional data science you have
solved for structured data so works best
for unstructured data so unstructured
data goes beyond just text is images and
videos and audios and other files but
let me just for simplicity sake talk
about text. So the first step would be
when you are ingesting this data to
store it in your knowledge base you need
to also do a lot of pre-processing
saying okay is all the information
useful are we unnecessarily extracting
information like for example if you have
a PDF file what sections of the PDF file
are you extracting or an HTML is a
better example like are you extracting
the entire HTML code or just the
snippets of information that you really
need. So another step that becomes
really important is called chunking.
Chunking of the data. And what chunking
means is that you might have documents
that run into hundreds and thousands of
pages, but for effective use in a rag
system, you need to sort of isolate
information or you need to break this
information down into smaller pieces of
text. And there are very many reasons
why you need to do that. First is the
context window that we talked about. you
can't fit a million words in the context
window. The second is that search
happens better if you have smaller
pieces of text, right? Like you can more
effectively search on a smaller piece of
text than an entire document. So
chunking becomes very important. Now all
this is text but computers work on
numerical data, right? They work on
numbers. So this text has to be
converted into a numerical format. And
traditionally there have been very many
ways of doing that. Text processing is
being done since ages. But one
particular data format that has gained
prominence in the NLP domain is
embeddings. It's called embeddings. And
embeddings is simply it's converting
text into numbers. But embeddings are
not just numbers. They are storing text
in a vector form. So it's a series of
number. It's an array of numbers. And
why it becomes important? There are
reasons for that is because it becomes
very easy to calculate similarity
between text when you're using vectors
and therefore embeddings become an
important data format. So all your text
needs to be first chunked and these
chunks then need to be converted into
embeddings and so that you don't have to
do it every time you are asking a
question. You also need to store these
embeddings and these embeddings are then
stored in specialized databases that
have become popular now which are called
vector databases which are sort of
databases that are efficient in storing
embeddings or vector form of data. So
this entire flow of data from source
system into your vector database forms
the indexing pipeline and this becomes a
very crucial component of your rack
system because if this is not optimized
and this is not performing well then
your rack system cannot be your
generation pipeline cannot be expected
to do well. Very interesting. So I
wanted to ask you I was just thinking
about it was not in my original list of
questions. When you talk about this
chunking, what happens is if the
chunking like suppose you you've got a
big sentence like Priyanka is
intelligent and Priyanka is gets into
one chunk and intelligent goes into
another chunk. I don't know. Do you have
like this distortion of the sentence
because of chunking is Yeah, I mean
that's a great question because it can
happen. So there are different chunking
strategies to deal with it but I'll talk
about the simplest one that helps
prevent this helps maintain that context
is that between two chunks you also
maintain some degree of overlap. So it's
like if I say Priyanka is a good person
and my chunk size is two words for
example. So Priyanka is a good person.
But if I maintain an overlap, so it'll
become Priyanka is a an a good person.
So that a is in both the chunks. So if I
expand this idea then first of all I
will chunk only at the end of sentence.
So I don't I don't break a sentence
completely and then I can have
overlapping sentences in adjacent chunks
so that I don't miss the context. Got
it. So when you search you'll be like
searching on both the places where like
to your nearest neighbors whatever.
Yeah. So even if I retrieve one chunk
Yeah. the last sentences of the previous
chunk will come. Okay. And the first few
sentences of the next chunk will come
even if I'm retrieving a single chunk.
Okay. That's interesting. So I think
some of us who are been say software
engineers for like quite some time I
think we've had a very similar concept
also in terms of we've had this like I
used to work in the oil and gas
industry. So we used to do these kind of
triangulations when we actually in
graphics programming where you actually
end up rendering a chunk of the earth's
surface for example. So like there might
be different types of rocks and so like
this where one rock differs from another
like that will be shown in
triangulations just as an example. And
so what happens is that when you
actually do the indexing for that data,
when you're actually rendering something
on the screen, you actually have the
previous surface as well as the next
surface as well. So I was just saying so
that something very similar. Yeah,
something very similar happens in
chunking also. So you're maintaining
context, right? You're not losing
information that was there in the
previous part. You're maintaining this
overlap. So that context is sort of it
holds together. Okay, that's very
interesting to know. I wanted to ask you
also in terms of since you're dealing
with a lot of text. I'm assuming that
performance is also a big issue. So do
you have like caching is that something
that's also a big part of the rag
enabled design? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Caching is very important. What kind of
vector database you are using becomes
very important. What kind of so when you
are searching and retrieving information
what kind of retrieval methodology or
retrieval algorithm you are using
becomes very important and more so in
case when we are dealing with LLMs
because every time you are going to the
LLM you are incurring a cost because
every time it is computing you're using
your resources so chunk size also plays
an important role like if I'm giving
large chunks to the LLM you are
incurring more cost. So number of chunks
you have to optimize. So there are
several things that play a part to
improve the performance of the system.
So there's a lot of experimentation that
needs to be done visav the user
expectations costs. So you need users
want answers immediately. So your system
cannot have latency but LLM inherently
introduce a latency to the system. And
if you're adding a layer of retrieval
before going to LLM that again increases
the latency of the system. So you have
to optimize all of this. So caching as
you said has become an important part in
all generative AI application. And it's
not just caching like regular caching.
It's something called semantic caching
where you're not just caching queries
and searching for the exact queries. you
are also going to the cache if the query
is somewhat similar to the cached query.
So if the semantic meaning of the two
queries is the same, you go to the cache
instead of going through the entire
workflow actually. So we've looked at
two different parts of like the data
sources chunking and we talked about
caching. So let me now talk a little bit
about the retrieval part. How do you do
the retrieving? Is the indexing pipeline
helping you with the retrieving? Right.
Retrieval is the core component of a
rack system. Like without retrieval,
there is no rag. So how that happens?
Let's talk about how you search things,
right? Like the simplest form of
searching text is your boolean search.
Like if I press Ctrl F on my word
processor and I type a word, the exact
matches will get highlighted, right? But
there is lack of context in that, right?
You know, so that's the simplest form of
searching. So think of it like if I'm
asking a query who won the 2023 cricket
world cup and that exact phrase is
present in a document I can do a control
f search for that fetch that and pass
that to the llm right that will be the
simplest form of search but practically
that does not work because the question
that the user is asking will not be
present in any document. So what do we
have to do now? We have to do like sort
of a semantic search. We have to grasp
the meaning of the question and then try
to find out okay which documents might
have the similar answer or which chunks
might have the similar answer. Now that
is done the most popular way of doing
that is through something called cosine
similarity. Now how is that done is I
talk about embeddings right like your
data your text is converted into a
vector. So vector is a series of numbers
that can be plotted in an n dimensional
space right like if I look at a graph
paper a you know a two-dimensional sort
of x-axis and y-axis a vector will be x
y. So my query also needs to be
converted into a vector form. So the
query goes through an embedding
algorithm and is converted into a vector
form. Now this query is then plotted on
the same vector space in which all the
chunks are also there. And now you're
trying to calculate which chunk the
vector of which chunk is closest to this
query. And that can be done through
that's a distance calculation like in
vector algebra or in quadrant geometry
that can be done through L1, L2, L3
distance calculations. But what is the
most popular way of doing that today in
rag systems is through something called
cosine similarity. So what you're trying
to do is between these two vectors your
query vectors and the document vectors
you are trying to calculate the cosine
of the angle between them angle from the
origin like if I draw a line from the
origin to the vector what is the angle
between so if it's zero means if it's
exactly similar cos 0 will be one right
if it's perpendicular orthogonal to your
query which is which means that there is
absolutely no similarity cos 90 will be
zero And if it's like exactly opposite
it'll be minus one something like that.
Right? So then this is the way how
identify which documents or which chunks
are similar to my query vector you know
similar to my question. So then I can
retrieve the chunk. I can retrieve one
chunk or I can retrieve top five chunks
or top two chunks. I can also have a
cutoff that hey if the cosine similarity
is less than 7 then just say that you
know I could not find anything that is
similar and then I retrieve these chunks
and then I can send it to the LLM for
further processing. So this is how
retrieval happens and there are
different algorithms but this embedding
based cosine similarity is one of the
more popular ones mostly used everywhere
today in rag systems.
Okay, this is really good and I think
the question I had on how similarity is
calculated is answered now because you
talked about you using this cosine for
actually doing the similarity. Now that
we've talked about the retrieval, I want
to dive a bit more into the augmentation
part and here we talked briefly about
prompt engineering when we did the
introduction but what are the different
types of prompts that can be given to
get better results. Can you maybe talk
us through that because there's a lot of
literature in your book also where you
talk about different types of prompt
engineering. Yeah. So let me mention a
few prompt engineering techniques
because that's what the augmentation
step more commonly is about. It's about
prompt engineering. Though there is also
a component of fine-tuning which that
becomes really complex. So let's just
think of augmentation as putting the
user query and the retrieve chunks or
retrieve documents together. So simple
way of doing that is hey this is the
question answer only based on these
chunks and I paste that in the prompt
send that to the LLM and LLM responds.
So that's the simplest way of doing it.
Now sometimes let's think about it what
happens if that answer to the question
is not there in the chunks the LLM might
still hallucinate. So another way of
dealing with that very intuitive way of
dealing with that is saying hey if you
can't find the answer just say I don't
know with this simple instruction the
LLM is able to process it and if it does
not find the answer then it'll you know
sort of generate that result. Now if I
want the answer to be in a certain
format saying what is the sentiment of
this particular piece of chunk and I
don't want positive negative I want say
for example angry jealous something like
this right and if I have specific
categorizations in my mind let's say I
want to categorize sentiments into A B
and C but the LLM does not know what A B
and C are I can give examples in the
prompt itself. So what I can say is
identify the sentiment in this retrieved
junk and here are a few examples of what
sentiments look like. So I paste a
paragraph and then say sentiment is A. I
paste another paragraph and I say
sentiment is B. Turns out that language
models are excellent at adhering to
these examples. This is something that
is called few short prompting. Few short
means that I am giving a few examples
within the prompt so that the LLM
responds in the similar manner as my
examples. So that's another way of you
know sort of prompt augmentation. Now
there are other techniques something
that has become very popular in
reasoning models today which is called
chain of thought. It basically provides
the LLM with the way it should reason
through the context and provide an
answer. Like for example, if I were to
ask who was the best team of the ODI
World Cup and then I also give it a set
of instructions saying hey this is how
you should reason step by step that is
prompting the LLM to sort of think like
not generate answer at once but think
about what the answer should be. That is
something called as chain of thought
reasoning and there are several others
but these are the ones that are mostly
popular and used in rack systems. Yeah,
in fact I've been uh doing this a course
just to understand get better at prompt
engineering and one of the things I
learned was also like we I'm working as
an example of a data pipeline you know
trying to use LLMs to produce SQL query
for a database and I found that exactly
what you're saying you know like if you
had given like some example queries on
how it should be you know give this is
the database this is like the data model
these are the particular examples like
if I ask you what is the product with
the highest review rating and I give it
an example example of what the SQL query
is then I feel that the answers are much
better than if I were to just ask the
question like can can you please produce
an SQL query for what is the highest
rating of a product. So I think it's
quite fascinating to see this the few
short prompting which you talked about
but also the chain of thought reasoning
it also helps with debugging right to
see how it's working. Yeah. Yeah.
Absolutely. And there are several others
that you can experiment with and see if
it works for your use case. But you know
prompt engineering is also not an exact
science. It's based on how well is the
LLM responding in your particular use
case. Okay, great. Uh so the next thing
which I want to talk about which is also
in your book which is chapter 4 where
you talk about generation how the
responses are generated based on
augmented prompts and here you talk
about the concept of the models which
are used in the LLM. So can you tell us
what are these foundational models?
Right. So as we said right LLMs they are
models that are trained on massive
amounts of data billions of parameters
in some cases trillions of parameters
they are not easy to train. So we we
know that open AAI has trained their
models which is the GPT series of
models. Meta has trained their own
models which are the llama series. Then
there is Gemini. There is Mistral. These
large models which have been trained on
data these are the foundation models.
These are sort of the base models. These
are called pre-trained models. Now if
you were to go to chat GPT and see how
the interaction happens. LMS as we said
are text prediction models. They are
trying to predict the next words in a
sequence. But that's not how chat GP
works, right? It's not like you're
giving it an incomplete sentence and
it'll it is completing that sentence.
It's actually responding to the
instruction that you have given to it.
Now, how does that happen? Because
technically LLMs are just next word
prediction models. So, how that is done
is through something called fine-tuning
which is you know instruction
fine-tuning. So how that happens is that
you have a data set in which you have
instructions or prompts and examples of
what the responses should be and then
there is the supervised learning process
that happens so that your foundation
model now starts generating responses in
this in the format of the example data
that you have provided. So these are
fine-tuned models. So you know what you
can also do is if you have a very
specific use case for example you know
complex things like medicine or law
where you know the terminology is very
specific is that you can take a
foundation model and fine-tune it for
your specific use case. So this is a
choice that you can make. Do you want to
take a foundation model for your rack
system? Do you want to fine-tune it with
your own data? So that's one way in
which you can look at you know the
generation component and the models. The
other ways to look at also is whether
you want a large model or a small model
whether you want to use a proprietary
model which is like open AAI has not
made their model public. So nobody knows
what are the parameters of those models
but they provide it to you through an
API. So but the model is then managed by
OpenAI right so that's like a
proprietary model but there are also
open-source models where everything is
given to you and you can host it on your
system so that's like an open-source
model that you can host it on your
system or there are other providers that
you know provide you with APIs for those
open source models so that's also a
choice that you need to make do you want
to go with a proprietary model or do you
want to take an open-source model and
use it you know the way you start to use
it. So that's you know sort of the
decision making that you have to do in
the generation component. How do you
decide whether you want to go for a
opensource versus a proprietary model?
Is is it a similar decision like as
software developers we also go between
sometimes you have these open source
libraries versus something that you can
actually buy a product like you can use
a bunch of open source libraries and
build a product yourself or just go and
buy something and then use that to do
your flow. How is that? Is it a very
similar way that you would think as the
decision-m between a pre-trained model
versus an open-source? Yeah. Yeah. I
would think of it in in a similar
fashion, you know, whether you want to
have that control of owning the entire
thing, hosting that entire thing or you
want to outsource it to the provider,
right? Like that is one way of looking
at it which is very similar to how you
know you would make the decision for any
software product that you're developing.
But there is another important aspect
which is around data privacy. So if
you're using a proprietary model that
the prompt along with the prompt
whatever you're sending goes to their
servers right they are going to do the
inferencing and send the response back
to you. But if you're not comfortable
with that and you want everything to be
in your environment, then there is no
other option but for you to host that
model yourself and that is only possible
for open-source models. Another way is
that if you really want to have the
control over fine-tuning the model
because what happens in proprietary
models is you just give them the data
and they will do everything else, right?
you give them the data that this is the
data that needs to be the model needs to
be fine-tuned on and then open AAI
providers will do that for you but if
you really want to sort of customize
even the fine-tuning process of the
model then you need to do it inhouse so
that's where open source models become
important so those are the two caveats
that I will put apart from all the
regular software application development
decision- making that you do I think
that's a brilliant answer I mean I I've
understood it because It's the privacy
angle as well as the fine-tuning angle
is a very good rule of thumb I think for
people who want to decide on using
either. Now that we've talked a little
bit, you know, just dipped into like the
rag components, I I wanted to ask you
about how do you do monitoring of a rag
system that you would do in a normal
system that you have, you have a lot of
anything goes wrong, you need to have
the monitoring to the logging to find
out. How does that happen with a rag
system? Is it pretty much the same thing
that you would do as for normal
software?
So all the components of monitoring that
you would imagine in a regular software
system all of that hold true for a rack
system also but there are also some
additional components that we should be
monitoring and that also takes me to the
evaluation of the rack system. So how do
you evaluate a rack system whether it is
performing well and then how you do you
monitor whether it continues to perform
well or not. And when we talk about
evaluation of rack systems, let's think
of it in terms of three components. One
is component one is the user's query,
the question that is being asked.
Component two is the answer that the
system is generating and component three
is the documents or the chunks that the
system is retrieving. Now let's look at
the interaction of these three
components. Let's look at the user query
and the retrieved documents. So the
question that I might ask is are the
documents that are being retrieved
aligned to the query that the user is
asking. So I will need to evaluate that
and there are several metrics there. So
my rack system should actually be
retrieving information that is as per
the question that is being asked. If it
is not then I have to improve that. The
second sort of dimension is the
interaction between the retrieved
documents and the answer that the system
is generating. So when I pass these
retrieved documents or retrieved chunks
to the LLM, does it really generate the
answers based on those documents or is
it generating answers from elsewhere?
That's another dimension that needs to
be evaluated. This is called the
faithfulness of the system. whether the
the generated answer is rooted in the
documents that are being retrieved and
then the final component to evaluate is
between the question and the answer like
is the answer really answering the
question that was being asked. So is
there relevance between the answer and
the question that was being asked. So
these are the three components of rag
evaluation and there are several metrics
in each of these three dimensions and
they need to be monitored uh you know
going forward but also think about this
what happens if the nature of queries
change. So I need to monitor if the
queries that are now coming to the
system are they same or similar to the
queries that the system was built on or
built for. So that's another thing that
we need to monitor. Similarly, if I'm
updating my knowledge base, right? So,
are the documents in the knowledge base
similar to how it was initially created
or do I need to go revisit that? So,
sort of as the time progresses, is there
a shift in the query? Is there a shift
in the documents? So, that those are
some additional components of
observability and monitoring, you know,
as we go into production. I think that
was the part which is I think chapter
five of your book which I also found
very interesting because you also talked
a little bit about benchmarking there to
see how the pipelines work better to see
how the models perform which was great.
Unfortunately we're close to the end of
the session so I have to ask you a few
more questions to sort of round off this
and we probably have to bring you back
for more on the book. You talked a
little bit about security in the
introduction and I wanted to ask you in
terms of security, what needs to be done
for a you know rag system. What should
you be thinking about when you're
building it? Oh yeah, that's an
important thing that we should discuss.
And first of all, I'll be very happy to
come on again and talk more about rags.
But when we talk about security and you
know the regular security, data
security, software security, those
things still hold for rag systems also.
But when it comes to NLMs, there is
another component of prompt injections.
Mhm. What has been observed is that
malicious actors can prompt the system
in a way that the system starts behaving
in an abnormal manner. The model itself
starts behaving in an abnormal manner.
We can think about it as a lot of
different things that can be done.
answering things that you're not
supposed to answer, revealing
confidential data, you know, start
generating responses that are not safe
for work like things like that. So the
rack system also needs to be protected
against prompt injections. So one way in
which prompt injections can be done is
direct prompting like if I in charge GBD
I can directly do some kind of prompting
that will change the behavior of the
system. In rag it becomes more important
because these prompt injections can be
there in the data itself the database
that I'm looking for. So that's like a
indirect sort of injection. Now how to
defend against them? There are several
ways of doing that. First is you build
guard rails around what your system can
and cannot do when the input is coming.
When an input prompt is coming you sort
of don't pass that directly to the LLM
for generation but you do a sanitization
there. you do some checks there.
Similarly for the data you know you need
to do that. So guardrailing is one
aspect. Then uh there's also processing
of you know sometimes you know there are
some special characters that are you
know added to the prompts or the data
which might makes the LLM behave in an
undesired manner. So all these removal
of you know unwanted characters,
unwanted spaces that also becomes an
important part. So that's another layer
of security that I would put in. But
mostly all the things that you would put
in a data system, a system that uses a
lot of data, all that become very
important in rag systems also. And this
defense against prompt injections is
another aspect of security that should
be cognizant of. I think the OASP
organization has come up with this OASP
top 10 for LLMs. So they talk a little
bit about how do you mitigate against
these attacks like prompt ejection like
you said input validation data poisoning
how to you know mitigate against that.
So that's something I'll add to the show
notes so people can look at that. The
last question I want to ask you is about
the future of rag. So it's like two
questions on that. One is what do you
think are the challenges that you see in
rag today and how will it improve? And
this when you talk about that can you
also talk a little bit about what is
egantic rag or agenti and agentic rag.
So tell us about that. There are several
challenges with rag systems today. There
are several kind of queries that uh you
know that vanilla rack systems are not
able to solve. There is something called
multihop reasoning in which you know
you're not just retrieving a document
and answer you'll find the answer there
but you have to go through several
iterations of retrieval and generation
you know for example if I were to ask
the celebrities that endorse brand A how
many of them also endorse brand B now
it's unlikely that this information will
be present in one document so what the
system will have to do is first of all
infer that this will not be present in
one document and then sort of establish
the connections between documents to be
able to answer a question like this.
This is sort of a multihop reasoning. So
you first hop onto one document, find
out information from there, go to
another document and get the answer from
there. This is sort of very effectively
being done by another variant of rag
called knowledger graph enhanced rags.
So knowledge graphs are these storage
patterns in which you know you establish
relationships between entities and so
when it comes to answering related
questions or questions that are related
and not just present in one place you
know it's an area of deep exploration.
So knowledge graph enhanced rag is one
of the direction in which rag is moving.
Another direction that rag is moving in
is taking in multimodal capabilities. So
not just being able to process text but
also being able to process images.
That's where we are right now in you
know processing images. But this will
continue to expand to audio, video and
other formats of unstructured data. So
multimodal rack becomes very important
and then like you said agentic AI is
sort of the buzzword and also the
direction in which is a natural
progression for all AI systems to move
towards or LLM based systems to move
towards and rag is also going in that
direction but these are not competing
things these are complimentary things.
So what does agentic AI mean? In very
simple words, and this is gross
oversimplification of things, but if my
LLM
is given the capability of making
decisions autonomously by providing it
memory in some way and access to a lot
of different tools like external APIs to
take actions
that becomes an autonomous agent. So my
LLM can reason, can plan, knows what has
happened in the past and then can take
an action through the use of some tools.
That is an AI agent very simplistically
put. Now think about it in terms of
rank. So what can be done? So agents can
be used at every step, right? For
processing of data, whether my data has
useful information or not. What kind of
chunking needs to be done? you know, I
can store my information in different
not in just one knowledge base, but I
can have several knowledge bases and
depending on the question, I can pick
and choose an an agent can pick and
choose which storage component should I
fetch from. Then when it comes to
retrieval, how many times should we
retrieve? Do I need to retrieve more?
Are there any additional things that I
need to look at? All these decisions can
be made by an agent. So at every step of
my rag workflow what I was doing in a
simplistic manner can be further
enhanced by putting in an agent there
putting in an L&M agent but then think
about it again it'll increase the
latency it'll increase the cost that all
has to be balanced so that's sort of the
direction that rag and all AI will take
apart from that there is also sort of
something in popular discourse is that
With the advent of LLMs that have long
context windows is rag going to die and
sort of funny discourse that goes on
happening. So today there is limitation
in which how much information can I put
in the prompt for that I need this whole
retrieval. What if there comes a time in
which the entire database can be put
into the prompt you know there is no
need for this retrieval component. So
then one thing is that cost really
increases right and so does latency when
I'm processing so much information but
also in terms of accuracy what we've
observed is that as things stand of
today a rag system will perform sort of
similar or better than you know long
context LLMs but that's also something
to watch out for like how does this
space evolve will the retrieval
component be required will it go away in
what cases will it be needed all that
questions are for us to wait and watch
this is great I think it's been very
fascinating discussion and I learned a
lot and I'm sure it's the same with the
listeners so thank you for coming on the
show Abina oh my pleasure it was a great
conversation and thank you for having me
here great this is Priyanka Ragan for
software engineering radio thanks for
listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by e
software or magazine. For more about the
podcast, including other episodes, visit
our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
seradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
teamseradio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Common
License 2.5. Thanks for listening.